<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>中国新闻-美国之音</title><link/>https://www.voanews.com/z/6715<description>美国之音中国新闻</description><image/><url>https://www.voanews.com/Content/responsive/VOA/en-US/img/logo.png</url><title>中国新闻-美国之音</title><link/>https://www.voanews.com/z/6715<language>恩</language><copyright>2023 - 美国之音</copyright><ttl>60</ttl><lastbuilddate> 2023 年 5 月 24 日星期三 08:44:52 -0400</lastbuilddate><generator> Pangea CMS——美国之音</generator><atom:link href="https://www.voanews.com/api/zmjuqteb_kqo" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><item><title>中国末代皇帝表在香港拍卖以创纪录的 620 万美元成交</title><description>中国清朝末代皇帝曾经拥有的一块手表周二在香港拍卖会上以创纪录的 620 万美元的价格售出，他的一生是奥斯卡获奖影片《末代皇帝》的原型。据拍卖行称，一位居住在香港的亚洲收藏家通过电话购买了属于爱新觉罗·溥仪的稀有百达翡丽手表。不包括买家佣金的落槌价为 510 万美元。拍卖行菲利普斯亚洲的手表主管 Thomas Perazzi 告诉路透社，这是曾经属于皇帝的所有手表的“最高成绩”。拍卖行称，这是仅有的八款已知百达翡丽 Reference 96 Quantieme Lune 时计之一，是溥仪在被苏联囚禁时送给他的俄罗斯翻译的礼物。它轻松超过了 300 万美元的预售估价。其他皇帝拥有并在拍卖会上出售的手表包括属于埃塞俄比亚末代皇帝海尔塞拉西的百达翡丽手表，2017 年以 290 万美元的价格售出。属于越南末代皇帝保大的劳力士手表拍得 5 美元百万在 2017 年的拍卖会上。溥仪出生于 1906 年，是中国清朝的最后一位皇帝，两岁即位。 1945年日本战败后，溥仪在沉阳机场被苏联红军俘虏。他作为战俘被关押在俄罗斯哈巴罗夫斯克的拘留营长达五年。该拍卖行表示，他们花了三年时间与手表专家、历史学家、记者和科学家合作，研究这块手表的历史并验证其出处。 Perazzi 告诉路透社，这只手表是当时百达翡丽制造的最好的手表。记者 Russell Working 在 2001 年采访了溥仪的翻译 Georgy Permyakov，他说他在苏联的最后一天将手表交给了 Permyakov，就在他被引渡回中国之前不久。 “这些是他有时对那些对他来说非常特别的人所做的事情，”工作说。</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/last-emperor-of-china-s-watch-sells-for-record-6-2-million-in-hong-kong-auction/7106705.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/last-emperor-of-china-s-watch-sells-for-record-6-2-million-in-hong-kong-auction/7106705.html</guid><pubDate> Wed, 24 May 2023 04:02:17 -0400</pubDate><category>中国新闻</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com（路透社） </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/012af390-f8f6-49b0-887b-ccf531c2e7c9_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title>美国不会在寻求谈判时接受中国的先决条件</title><description>美国国务院一位高级官员周二告诉美国之音，美国不会接受中华人民共和国设定的先决条件，同时寻求与北京保持开放的沟通渠道。与此同时，这位官员表示，没有太多迹象表明中国愿意利用其对俄罗斯的影响力来结束对乌克兰的战争。美国国务院参赞德里克·乔莱特星期二在 6 月中旬举行的全球使团团长会议之前向美国之音国务院分社社长 Nike Ching 谈到了中国和乌克兰，届时美国大使将返回华盛顿参加会议。为简洁明了起见，对以下采访摘录进行了编辑。美国之音：你能告诉我们乌克兰在夏季来临之际的春季反攻吗？美国国务院参赞德里克·肖莱特：我们一直在向乌克兰和我们的其他 50 个联盟伙伴提供他们保卫自己和夺回领土所需的资源。我要让乌克兰人自己就他们反攻的时机和他们的目标是什么来说话。美国之音：哪些国家愿意或已经承诺向乌克兰提供F-16？我们在看什么数字？ CHOLLET：我们现在正在研究这些细节。我们五角大楼的同事正在与整个欧洲和其他地方的国防部密切合作，讨论 F-16 的前进方向。必须从训练开始，因为这些都是不容易操作的飞机。他们需要数周又数周的培训。我们仍在研究谁将真正提供这些飞机。我们还没有为自己做出任何决定。我不认为它会成为一个与即将到来的反攻特别相关的系统，因为时机。但是，尽管如此，当我们考虑乌克兰对未来的需求，以及它持续的威慑和自卫需求时，这些飞机将成为现代乌克兰军队的重要组成部分。美国之音：你能谈谈乌克兰为挑战俄罗斯在全球南方的影响力而采取的外交行动吗？因为乌克兰外交部长德米特罗·库列巴本周将开始他的非洲之行。肖莱特：外交部长库列巴和[乌克兰]总统[弗拉基米尔]泽伦斯基和整个乌克兰领导层都下定决心要在全世界、世界各个角落处理他们的案子。没有比乌克兰领导层更能为乌克兰辩护的人了，因此我们非常支持他们的努力。我知道泽伦斯基总统成功访问了吉达并参加了阿拉伯联盟首脑会议。我知道他们也在与中东合作伙伴接触。美国之音：据媒体报道，中国特使李辉在前往俄罗斯之前，正在访问位于布鲁塞尔的欧盟总部。您如何评价中国的维和努力？中国有公信力吗？肖莱特：中国人现在正在与乌克兰人交谈，而且有一位特使来访，这是一件好事。坦率地说，我对这项工作抱有适度的期望。我的意思是，中国能做的最有帮助的事情就是试图向[俄罗斯总统弗拉基米尔]普京提出理由并让弗拉基米尔普京停止这场战争。重要的是要注意，如果弗拉基米尔普京决定从乌克兰撤军，这场战争可能会在明天结束。我看不到任何证据表明普京很快就会考虑这个问题。美国之音：澄清一下，美国是否认为中华人民共和国与普京有关联？肖莱：很明显，他们与俄罗斯有着密切的关系。习近平主席和普京总统多次会面，在这场战争之前，他们发表了一份非常冗长的联合公报，谈到了一种关系，一种没有限制的伙伴关系。我们会要求我们的中国朋友做的是利用他们对俄罗斯的任何影响力让普京停止这场战争。我没有看到太多迹象表明他们愿意利用这种影响力。而且我还没有看到太多迹象表明，即使他们愿意利用这种影响力，也能改变普京的想法。但这是我们要问的简单事情。美国之音：继续美中关系：国家安全顾问杰克沙利文最近与中国高级外交官王毅的会面对俄罗斯来说是个坏消息吗？肖莱：好吧，我不想谈论这对俄罗斯来说是坏消息还是好消息。我们的国家安全顾问和王毅之间的一次非常务实的会面讨论了美中关系，并从我们这边直截了当地谈论了我们看到的来自中国的一些挑战，我们之间的一些根本分歧跟他们。但同样重要的是，谈论我们继续希望能够与中国实现对话与合作的领域。我们再次与中国存在一些根本差异，我们将忠于我们的原则和价值观以及我们在那里的利益。但与此同时，我们认为与中国进行对话以讨论我们如何处理这些分歧以及我们如何为这种关系设置护栏很重要。美国之音：沙利文和王是否会定期会面，比如每季度一次？ CHOLLET：嗯，不，例会根本没有决定。几个月前，[安东尼] 布林肯国务卿离启程前往北京只有几个小时的路程，直到中国人不负责任且不可接受地在美国上空放了一个监视气球。所以，这是一个我们非常希望能够在某个时候重新开始的对话。目前还没有这方面的计划。没有决定对话的频率。重要的是我们愿意进行这种对话，这就是我们向中国提出的情况。美国之音：你能告诉我们美国驻华大使尼古拉斯伯恩斯下个月在华盛顿举行的使团长会议上的会面吗？肖莱特：尼克·伯恩斯是美国现代史上最有成就的外交官之一。我们非常相信他的判断，我们很高兴他接受了这项艰巨的任务，回到北京服役。就在上周，他在北京举行了几次会议，帮助讨论我们将如何努力在我们有护栏的地方建立这种关系，我们在它上面，下面有一个地板，以帮助支持它。因此，我们将期待他对进展情况的第一手印象。美国之音：中国官员表示有必要稳定与美国的关系。但与此同时，他们也要求美国停止加强与台湾的关系，停止对贸易和技术施加限制。有那些先决条件？ CHOLLET：我们当然不会接受任何东西。让中国自己来说明他们对与我们进行任何形式的对话都设定了什么样的条件。我们非常清楚，我们不会减少对印太地区或任何地方的盟友和伙伴的承诺。我们将继续捍卫我们的利益并忠于我们的价值观。在这样做的同时，还有与中国或其他任何人进行对话的空间。</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/us-won-t-accept-china-s-preconditions-while-pursuing-talks/7106591.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/us-won-t-accept-china-s-preconditions-while-pursuing-talks/7106591.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 22:00:21 -0400</pubDate><category>美国</category><category>东亚</category><category>中国新闻</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Nike Ching) </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/01000000-c0a8-0242-f034-08db5bfa16c2_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title>中国公民就“仇外”财产法起诉佛罗里达州</title><description>居住在佛罗里达州的四名中国公民和一家在该州经营的房地产经纪公司联手对一项新法律提起诉讼，该法律严格限制了一些非美国公民在那里购买房产的能力。 Shen v. Simpson 案指控佛罗里达州州长 Ron DeSantis 本月签署并于 7 月 1 日生效的佛罗里达州法律 SB 264 侵犯了原告根据美国宪法享有的平等保护权和正当程序权。该法案对古巴、委内瑞拉、叙利亚、伊朗、俄罗斯和朝鲜等“受关注国家”的公民个人购买房产进行了限制，但对中国公民的规定最为严格。根据法律规定，非美国合法永久居民的中国公民在佛罗里达州购买任何房地产均属违法行为。目前在该州拥有财产的中国公民将被要求向该州登记这些财产。违反法律可处以罚款、刑事指控和监禁。该诉讼列出了几名被告，其中包括佛罗里达州农业专员威尔顿·辛普森 (Wilton Simpson)，该机构将负责执法。佛罗里达州农业和消费者服务部尚未回应美国之音的置评请求。亚裔关注 该法案的反对者表示，该法案将增加该州的种族仇恨，并指出该法案与 19 世纪末和 20 世纪初美国通过的许多反华反亚裔法律相呼应，后来被裁定违宪。美国公民自由联盟国家安全项目副主任帕特里克图米对美国之音说：“佛罗里达州的亚裔美国人社区和其他受这项法律影响的社区非常担心它如何污名化亚裔后裔。” . “这将使任何名字听起来像是[来自]其中一个国家的人更难在该州购买房产。” “针对中国的仇外政策和言论助长了种族偏见，”亚裔美国人法律辩护和教育基金会的法律主任贝瑟尼·李在一份声明中说。 “我们一再看到以国家安全为名的政策是如何伤害亚裔美国人的——从移民限制到二战期间将日裔美国人关进营地，再到 9/11 事件后的监视。未能指出歧视性影响意味着我们的社区将继续经历种族主义、暴力和权利的侵蚀。” “所有亚裔美国人都会感受到佛罗里达州这项法律所带来的耻辱和寒蝉效应，就像一百多年前歧视我们祖先的法律一样，”美籍华人法律辩护律师 Clay Zhu 的联合创始人联盟在一份声明中说。 “我们不会回去的。”两党支持 该法案是在今年早些时候提出的，此前德桑蒂斯预计将于周三宣布参选共和党总统候选人，他表示希望阻止中国公司和国民在该州购买房产。该法案在州议会中有共和党和民主党的支持者。它以 95 票对 17 票的两党优势在参议院和众议院获得一致通过。然而，在上个月的一次听证会上，当超过 100 名华裔美国人出来抗议该法案并警告说这将助长反亚裔种族主义时，议员们试图向他们保证，该法案的意图不是伤害目前的任何人住在佛罗里达州。 “该法案唯一歧视的人是中国共产党，”佛罗里达州共和党众议员大卫·博雷罗 (David Borrero) 上个月在一次听证会上说。 “唯一担心买不到这里土地的人？那些不住在这里的人。”这一说法得到了民主党州代表凯瑟琳沃尔德伦的回应。 “我认为那个房间里的每个人都可能不包括在这项法案中，”她在听证会后说。 “我们并不想伤害住在这里的任何人。”法律并非独一无二 至少有 13 个州的法律禁止或限制外国拥有专门用于农业的土地。根据国会研究局收集的数据，2021 年只有约 3.1% 的私人农地为外国人或公司所有。在今年早些时候穿越美国部分地区的中国间谍气球引发争议之后，一个其他一些州也出台了类似的立法。佛罗里达州对住宅和其他财产的关注使其成为第一个将外国所有权禁令扩大到农业用地以外的法案，但它不太可能是最后一个。例如，得克萨斯州的立法者一直在考虑禁止中国、俄罗斯或伊朗公民在该州拥有房屋的立法。美国公民自由联盟 (ACLU) 的图米 (Toomey) 表示，他的组织已经确定了针对十几个不同州的外国财产所有权的新立法。世界范围内普遍存在的限制 对外国人拥有住宅物业的限制虽然对美国来说是新事物，但在世界范围内并不少见。出于各种原因采用此类法律，包括对国家安全、洗钱和高房价的担忧。 1 月，加拿大开始执行一项新法律，禁止外国投资者在两年内购买住宅物业。该措施旨在降低膨胀的住房成本，立法者认为部分原因是非公民购房造成的。今年年初，包括马略卡岛、梅诺卡岛和伊维萨岛在内的西班牙巴利阿里群岛政府游说禁止非公民在那里购买住宅，声称富有的外国人将房价推高至如此之高，以至于当地人再也负担不起居住费用那里。其他欧洲国家也对寻求购买住宅的外国人施加限制，包括奥地利、丹麦、意大利和瑞士。在某些情况下，法律已经存在了几十年。</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/chinese-citizens-sue-florida-over-xenophobic-property-law/7106207.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/chinese-citizens-sue-florida-over-xenophobic-property-law/7106207.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 20:24:32 -0400</pubDate><category>美国</category><category>东亚</category><category>中国新闻</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com（罗伯·加弗） </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/01000000-0aff-0242-d7d1-08db3c86cc08_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title>中国新任驻美大使承认两国关系面临挑战</title><description>中国新任驻华盛顿大使谢锋周二表示，他将寻求加强中美合作，但两国关系面临严峻挑战。 “我来这里是为了维护中国的利益。这是我的神圣职责，”谢在降落在纽约市约翰肯尼迪国际机场后告诉记者。 “我也是中国人民的使者，所以我来这里是为了加强中美交流与合作，”谢说，随着战略对手之间关系恶化，他经常直言不讳地指责美国的行动。涉及从台湾到贸易的一系列问题。 59 岁的谢最近担任外交部副部长，负责监督对美政策，许多分析人士表示，世界上最大的两个经济体之间的关系处于自 1979 年正式建立以来最糟糕的状态。谢在离开机场登上一辆面包车前说，两国关系面临“严重的困难和挑战”。中国官员说他会开车去华盛顿。谢说一口流利的英语，曾两次被派往中国驻华盛顿大使馆，2 月，谢提出了中国的正式谴责，称华盛顿在飞越美国上空引发外交危机后“顽固地”击落了它怀疑是中国间谍气球的行为。北京方面辩称这是一艘民用飞艇。美国国务院发言人马修·米勒表示，美方对谢的到来表示欢迎。 “我们期待与候任大使及其团队合作，”米勒说。 “正如我们在多个场合所说，我们仍然致力于保持与中华人民共和国的沟通渠道，以负责任地管理竞争。”</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/new-chinese-ambassador-to-us-acknowledges-challenges-in-relations-/7106047.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/new-chinese-ambassador-to-us-acknowledges-challenges-in-relations-/7106047.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 17:33:46 -0400</pubDate><category>中国新闻</category><category>美国</category><category>东亚</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com（路透社） </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/01000000-0aff-0242-c94c-08db5bcf4bab_cx0_cy9_cw0_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title>美国主要官员称中国的间谍气球“影响不大”</title><description>一位美国高级国防官员认为中国使用监视气球是一种分散注意力的行为，称与北京日益增强的太空军事化能力所带来的更大问题相比，它们无关紧要。自今年 2 月五角大楼宣布正在追踪其中一个飞越美国大陆的高空装置以来，中国对间谍气球的使用就成了头条新闻。从那以后，美国击落了一些中国气球和其他可疑的高空物体，有时使用了先进的武器，美国官员甚至承认气球能够收集敏感军事地点周围的一些信息。但空军部长弗兰克肯德尔周一表示，在某些方面，中国使用气球（北京称之为气象气球）是一种干扰。 “他们有一个非常积极的情报收集计划。气球只是其中很小的一部分，并不是很重要，”肯德尔在华盛顿的国防作家小组简报会上告诉记者。肯德尔说，更让他担心的是更高的职位。 “它的太空部分非常重要，也非常重要，”他说，“他们正在将天基能力与作战部队联系起来。”其他美国官员同样对中国在太空领域的进步发出了警告。 “中国认为太空是美国的一个潜在弱点，”国防情报局中国任务组负责人道格韦德在今年 3 月表示。 “中国有各种各样的太空和反太空资产或能力让我们非常担心，”韦德说，他称北京的太空计划“仅次于美国”。美国太空行动负责人钱斯·萨尔茨曼将军同样对北京日益增强的实力发出警告，称中国是“我们进出太空的最大威胁”。肯德尔周一特别表示，中国越来越有能力利用其卫星追踪美国军队和资产，这让他“非常担心”。 “这种作战能力的很大一部分是监视、侦察、瞄准……做一些事情，比如试图瞄准航空母舰、试图瞄准机动部队、各种类型的地面部队，”他说。 “这对他们来说可能是一个巨大的效率提升。”尽管肯德尔等官员请求立法者关注中国的太空能力，但一些立法者一直在推动解决高空气球的潜在威胁。参议院国防拨款小组委员会主席、民主党人乔恩·特斯特在上个月的一次听证会上说：“[美国北方司令部指挥官]告诉我们，他对空军的地平线和远程远征雷达有额外的资金需求。” “我们需要提供资源，我认为过道两边的这个委员会都希望确保我们的国家安全并提供资源来做到这一点，”特斯特补充说。空军的肯德尔呼吁立法者按时通过国防预算并支持现代化工作，包括进行改革，使空军能够更灵活地更好地应对中国的进步。 “对我们空军基地的威胁，对我们航母的威胁，他们的空中优势驱动......都已经持续了很长一段时间，我认为我们没有尽快做出反应，”他说，并补充说在某些情况下，“我们无缘无故地向中国赠送了一年多的时间。”</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/key-us-official-says-china-s-spy-balloons-not-highly-consequential/7105300.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/key-us-official-says-china-s-spy-balloons-not-highly-consequential/7105300.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 09:22:26 -0400</pubDate><category>美国</category><category>东亚</category><category>中国新闻</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com（杰夫塞尔丁） </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/06a20000-0aff-0242-03ec-08db0603b459_cx0_cy5_cw0_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title>初步报告称中国渔船倾覆无人生还</title><description>根据周二公布的初步政府调查，一艘载有来自中国、印度尼西亚和菲律宾的 39 名船员的渔船上周在印度洋倾覆，无人生还。 5月16日，这艘中国船只翻覆，船上有17名中国人、17名印度尼西亚人和5名菲律宾人。北京交通运输部在官方社交媒体帖子中说：“从倾覆船的分析来看……初步判断该船无人生还。”这艘船在澳大利亚广阔的搜救区域内倾覆，该区域位于西澳大利亚州首府珀斯以西 5,000 公里处。中国官方媒体周一报道说，中国和斯里兰卡的救援船发现了七具尸体，但没有具体说明死者的国籍。澳大利亚派出三架飞机和四艘船协助国际搜救工作。中国交通运输部表示，截至周二上午，救援行动已降级为“48 小时小规模调查”。据该部称，救援人员拖网了大约 64,000 平方公里的区域，“没有发现任何幸存者的迹象”。上周，飓风法比安在该地区掀起高达 7 米的海浪和每小时 120 公里的强风时，首次检测到这艘渔船的遇险信标。恶劣的天气条件推迟了救援工作，堪培拉的联合救援协调中心警告说生存条件“具有挑战性”。中国交通运输部表示，周二凌晨，救援船已鸣笛哀悼一分钟，到中午时分，现场只剩下七艘船。 “沉船状况与前一天相比无明显变化，并逐渐向东北方向漂移，”该部称。这艘倾覆的船只归蓬莱京鲁渔业公司所有，该公司是中国主要的国营渔业公司之一。根据北太平洋渔业委员会的说法，它被授权捕捞霓虹飞乌贼和太平洋秋刀鱼。根据 MarineTraffic 跟踪网站，该船于 5 月 5 日离开南非开普敦前往韩国釜山，该网站最后一次定位该船是在 5 月 10 日，该船位于印度洋法国小岛留尼汪东南方。蓬莱京鹭渔业还在国际水域（包括印度洋和拉丁美洲周边海域）经营鱿鱼和金枪鱼捕捞业务。</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/no-survivors-in-chinese-fishing-vessel-capsizing-initial-report-says/7105175.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/no-survivors-in-chinese-fishing-vessel-capsizing-initial-report-says/7105175.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 07:19:32 -0400</pubDate><category>中国新闻</category><category>东亚</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com（法新社） </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/01000000-0aff-0242-307b-08db5b7f57f6_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title>国际刑警组织成立 100 周年之际，对其红色通报系统滥用的批评依然存在</title><description>国际刑警组织成立于 1923 年，旨在促进执法机构之间的合作，近年来已转变为一支强大的打击犯罪力量。然而，最近关于专制政权滥用其警报系统的争议为其作为全球执法合作不可或缺的工具的声誉蒙上了阴影。司法部副部长丽莎·莫纳科 (Lisa Monaco) 周一在司法部纪念国际刑警组织成立一百周年的活动上发表讲话，称赞该组织在应对从恐怖主义到网络犯罪和人口贩运等新兴全球威胁方面发挥的作用。 “在过去的 100 年里，国际刑警组织不断发展以应对这些威胁中的每一个，并在这样做的过程中使世界变得更加安全，”摩纳哥告诉与会者。在司法部著名的人民大会堂举行的仪式上，一支管鼓乐队和当地警察局的一名旗帜卫士进行了演讲。国际刑警组织高级官员以及司法部和国土安全部的高级官员出席了会议，这两个机构负责管理国际刑警组织在华盛顿的美国国家中央局。国际刑警组织发布红色通缉令，要求世界各地的警察部队找到并逮捕等待引渡的嫌疑人。国际刑警组织 195 个成员国中的任何一个国家都可以申请红色通缉令，只要它符合其规则。国际刑警组织表示，2016 年成立了一个由律师和警官组成的工作组，对所有红色通缉令请求和通缉犯传播进行彻底审查。扩散是一个成员国向其他成员国发送的警报。此外，国际刑警组织有一个独立机构，称为国际刑警组织文件控制委员会，负责从其系统中删除有争议的红色通告和其他警报。该委员会主要由律师组成，对虐待行为进行额外的审查。然而，尽管该机构努力确保合规性，俄罗斯和中国等国家近年来仍被指控出于政治目的滥用国际刑警组织的警报系统。国际刑警组织秘书长于尔根斯托克在司法部仪式上为其机构的“稳健”审查制度辩护。斯托克说：“当反复出现不合规情况时，这些成员国将采取预防和纠正措施，以保护我们渠道的完整性。”国际刑警组织的数据显示，该机构驳回了大量不合规的请求。 2021 年，国际刑警组织发布了近 24,000 份红色通缉令和通缉令，同时驳回了近 1,300 份违规通缉令。摩纳哥赞扬国际刑警组织加强对警报请求和传播的审查，以“确保国际刑警组织不被专制政权滥用以促进跨国镇压”。但这并没有阻止专制政权滥用该制度，批评人士说。 2021 年，根据国际刑警组织应中国要求发布的红色通缉令，中国受迫害的维吾尔族少数民族维权人士伊德里斯·哈桑 (Idris Hasan) 在摩洛哥被捕。尽管国际刑警组织在哈桑被捕后将红色简报归类为“不合规”，但该案件凸显了“国际警务组织与非法治国家合作的内在危险，这些国家容易滥用此类工具进行迫害，这与国际刑警组织的宪法背道而驰”，人类非营利组织 Safeguard Defenders 在一份报告中写道。批评人士说，俄罗斯是国际刑警系统的另一个连环滥用者。近年来，俄罗斯多次要求国际刑警组织发布红色通缉令，逮捕美国人权活动家、俄罗斯总统普京的批评者比尔·布劳德。 2018 年，布劳德声称他是根据“俄罗斯逮捕令”在西班牙被捕的，但国际刑警组织发言人告诉美国之音，她可以确认“没有对鲍德先生发出红色通缉令”。传统基金会高级研究员泰德·布罗蒙德 (Ted Bromund) 表示，国际刑警组织的运作基于其成员国善意行事的假设。 “结果，国际刑警组织通过通知、传播和其他机制继续滥用职权，”布罗蒙德在接受采访时说。 Bromund 表示，国际刑警组织的数据表明，其审查工作组未能阻止中国和俄罗斯等国家提交的可疑红色通缉令。他指出，国际刑警组织文件控制委员会删除的通知数量仍然是“历史最高水平”。 “如果通知和传播特别工作组真的在防止所有滥用行为，委员会……不应该继续删除这么多红色通知，”他说。国际刑警组织发言人雷切尔比灵顿对比较这两个数字表示异议。 “在评估红色通告的合规性时，工作组会考虑当时可用的信息，”比林顿在给美国之音的电子邮件中写道。 “如果或何时提供新信息，可以审查通知，如果发现不再合规，工作组将取消通知，并通知所有成员国。”中国和俄罗斯都否认滥用国际刑警组织。撇开所谓的红色通缉令滥用职权不谈，国际刑警组织在全球执法合作中仍然发挥着重要作用。近年来，随着犯罪分子越来越多地跨境和在线活动，它在打击犯罪方面的作用越来越大。国际刑警组织表示，全球警察部门每天查询其数据库超过 2000 万次，即每秒大约 250 次搜索。</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/as-interpol-turns-100-criticism-persists-over-abuse-of-its-red-notice-system/7105037.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/as-interpol-turns-100-criticism-persists-over-abuse-of-its-red-notice-system/7105037.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 03:18:10 -0400</pubDate><category>欧洲</category><category>中国新闻</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Masood Farivar) </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/16DDAA55-19CD-45BA-A9C7-BC9BD5311758_cx0_cy9_cw0_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title>香港特首谴责要求退出器官捐献系统的要求</title><description>香港行政长官李家超谴责要求退出香港器官捐献系统的请求数量异常上升，并表示警方将调查可疑案件。据政府称，自去年 12 月政府提出与中国大陆建立器官移植互助计划的可能性以来，该市的集中器官捐献登记系统在五个月内收到了近 5,800 份退出申请。超过一半的撤回申请被发现无效，要么是重复申请，要么来自从未选择加入的人。在例行新闻发布会上，李指出那些从未注册就撤回申请的人，称这些举动可疑。他说：“我严厉谴责那些企图破坏这个通过器官捐献拯救生命的崇高制度的人。” “这是一种可耻的行为。”政府周一还发表了措辞强硬的声明，称不排除有少数人试图退出，以破坏系统的声誉，增加行政负担。它没有点名任何平台或任何个人，只是说它注意到少数人通过宣传捐赠者应该在线审查接受者身份的想法来扭曲器官捐赠的优点。 Some also urged others to withdraw from the system, it added. On Hong Kong&#39;s Reddit-like forum LIHKG — where pro-democracy supporters discussed strategies for the 2019 anti-government movement — some users were skeptical about the proposed system. Others posted a link for withdrawing from the register. The government floated the proposal after a baby girl underwent the city&#39;s first transplant using an organ donated from mainland China in December. It said the organ assistance program under consideration could be activated immediately after medical personnel could not match a donated organ with a suitable patient locally. The political row over the proposed mutual assistance program reflected some Hong Kongers&#39; distrust of China&#39;s health system, as well as their grievances toward Beijing, which has cracked down on the city&#39;s pro-democracy movement with a sweeping national security law.</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/hong-kong-leader-condemns-requests-to-leave-organ-donation-system/7105030.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/hong-kong-leader-condemns-requests-to-leave-organ-donation-system/7105030.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 03:05:55 -0400</pubDate><category> China News</category><author> webdesk@voanews.com (Associated Press) </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/01000000-0aff-0242-04ca-08db5b5be6cc_cx0_cy5_cw0_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Beijing&#39;s Latest Strike in US-China Chip War May Hurt China, Experts Say</title><description> Just after the G7 Hiroshima Summit ended, China&#39;s Cyberspace Administration of China, or CAC, issued a statement requesting that &quot;operators of critical information infrastructures in China should stop purchasing products made by Micron Technology&quot; due to &quot;national security risks.&quot; The US Department of Commerce dismissed the ban issued Sunday as &quot;unsubstantiated,&quot; while Micron, the biggest US memory chipmaker, said in a written statement, &quot;We have received CAC&#39;s notice. … We are evaluating the conclusion and assessing our next steps. We look forward to continuing to engage in discussions with Chinese authorities.&quot; VOA Mandarin&#39;s email requesting Micron&#39;s comments on whether it will appeal China&#39;s decision or consult with the US government went unanswered as of the press time. The news of China&#39;s decision to block Micron after nearly two months of investigation came as a shock to the foreign business community in China. The company is the first US chipmaker to be targeted by Beijing after Washington in October placed export controls on some American-made components and tools for chipmaking to prevent them from being used to expand China&#39;s military capabilities. Michael Hart, president of the Beijing-based American Chamber of Commerce in China (AmCham China), said in a written response to VOA Mandarin on Monday that US businesses are worried about being the next target of China&#39;s security review. Hart said in his emailed reply, &quot;Our members are asking us two things: will they be targeted because they are American, and how can they ensure they remain compliant in a business environment that appears to be increasingly influenced by national security concerns?&quot; Representatives of AmCham China expressed concerns about the Micron case in late April. When asked about the case at a video news conference on April 26, Lester Ross, chairman of the Chamber&#39;s policy committee, said that China&#39;s &quot;taking action against particular foreign individuals or companies…It is a major concern because China lacks transparency in many dimensions in law and policies. In the absence of data and real evidence showing that Micron&#39;s products are understood as an example is of particular vulnerability to China.&quot; He said &quot;it is a concern on the part of other companies, in other industries as well that they could suddenly be singled out without any clear evidence being presented on the basis of unclear suspicions [and] that their ability to do business…will be jeopardized and their investment will go away.&quot; Hart said at the same news conference that China was traditionally known for its &quot;predictable investment environment, whether that be predictable rules and places to invest.&quot; But recent Chamber polls show that US businesses are less comfortable with the predictability. The uncertainty comes from both last year&#39;s COVID controls and China&#39;s increasing security probes. European businesses also worry European companies in China are also worried, especially about the possible impact on the semiconductor supply chain. Jörg Wuttke, president of the European Union Chamber of Commerce in China, said in a Monday email response to VOA Mandarin that the chamber issued a report in January 2021 outlining the impact that decoupling will have on company operations. In this regard, he wrote, &quot;geopolitical and COVID 19-releated factors have shone a spotlight on the fragility of global supply chains, including their susceptibility to chip shortages.&quot; As a result, Wuttke said, the Micron case &quot;could potentially add to these [supply chain] pressures.&quot; He said, &quot;European companies operating in China need to closely monitor the situation, evaluate the risk that the US-China technology competition poses to their supply chains, and make contingency plans accordingly.&quot; Founded in 1978 and headquartered in Idaho, Micron is the leading memory chip company in the US and the third-largest memory chipmaker in the world, behind Samsung and SK Hynix in South Korea. Micron&#39;s main products are DRAM (dynamic random access memory) and NAND Flash (flash memory). According to the company&#39;s 2022 financial report, DRAM accounts for about 73% of total revenue and flash memory accounts for 25%, for 98% of total revenue. Micron&#39;s products are used in cell phones, personal computers and servers. Their components can be found in the automotive, industrial and consumer markets as well. China, the world&#39;s biggest semiconductor buyer, has gradually reduced its reliance on foreign-made chips as part of a years-long push to develop self-sufficiency. Micron has offices in Shanghai, Xi&#39;an and Shenzhen, China, and a test and assembly facility in Xi&#39;an. Because of the US-China trade war, China is no longer Micron&#39;s largest market. China revenue has reportedly plummeted from 57% of its global revenue in 2018, or about $17 billion, to 10.8% last year, or about $3.26 billion, according to its 2022 financial report and other reports. Escalated sanctions In an interview with VOA Mandarin, Lin Tsung-Nan, a professor at the Department of Electrical Engineering at National Taiwan University in Taipei, said that in the face of the G-7 joint statement on China, Chinese President Xi Jinping must show toughness with nationalistic sentiment to the Chinese people. Externally, based on a confrontational strategy, Xi must also show the democratic and free world that he is capable of imposing sanctions, Lin said. He said blocking Micron is a geopolitical retaliation, one that hurts China and others. &quot;This is a bit like the &#39;Seven Wounded Fist&#39; in martial arts novels, which will hurt Micron and of course itself [China],&quot; Lin said. &quot;However, China should have calculated, that is, when it hurt itself, it&#39;s not fatal.&quot; According to the Wuxia Fandom Wiki the skill Lin refers to &quot;allows the user to inflict severe internal injuries on his opponent while suffering grave internal injuries at the same time.&quot; He said that even if the ban on Micron hurts the domestic market, the Chinese Communist Party would not hesitate to do this to defend its authority. In addition, after the Micron ban takes effect, South Korea will likely play an &quot;important but awkward&quot; role, Lin said, explaining that with Micron&#39;s exit, South Korea&#39;s Samsung and Hynix may take over Micron&#39;s market share. This is especially true for Samsung, which has made extensive DRAM production investment in China. Samsung&#39;s recent poor sales in China will motivate it to grab the share, Lin said. Even if Seoul is constrained by Washington&#39;s request for South Korean factories not to export supplies to China, the Chinese Communist Party may exert pressure on Samsung&#39;s Chinese factories for &quot;secret deals,&quot; according to Lin, who added, &quot;This is Xi&#39;s plan to kill two birds with one stone: to show China&#39;s assertiveness, and to rope in South Korea, or to divide South Korea and the US on their China stance.&quot; Micron Once An Espionage Victim In an ironic twist, Micron was once the alleged victim of Chinese theft of trade secrets. In 2018, a federal grand jury in San Francisco charged a Chinese state firm, a Taiwanese chipmaker, and three employees with economic espionage related to a conspiracy to steal Micron&#39;s trade secrets. The case centered on Taiwan-based United Microelectronics Corp.&#39;s role in illegally transferring Micron&#39;s DRAM technology to China&#39;s Fujian Jinhua Integrated Circuit Co Ltd. The UMC employees once worked for Micron&#39;s Taiwan subsidiary. Before leaving Micron, JT Ho and Kenny Wang allegedly stole and brought to UMC several Micron trade secrets related to the design and manufacture of DRAM, proscutors said. . Stephen Chen allegedly brokered a deal to transfer DRAM technology from UMC to Jinhua for mass production. He later became Jinhua&#39;s president and was put in charge of its DRAM production facility. UMC pleaded guilty in 2020 to one count of receiving and possessing a trade secret. It agreed to pay a fine of $60 million and cooperate with US prosecutors. In a statement, UMC denied any knowledge of the theft of Micron&#39;s trade secrets or their unauthorized transfer to Jinhua. VOA reached out to Jack DiCanio, a lawyer for Jinhua, but did not immediately receive a response. Jinhua has pleaded not guilty and has been fighting the charges in federal court in San Francisco. In court documents, US prosecutors said China lacked DRAM technology before the alleged theft of Mircon&#39;s trade secrets and had identified it as a &quot;national economic priority.&quot; Jinhua was created in 2016 with $5.65 billion in funding from the Chinese government for the “sole purpose” of designing, developing, and manufacturing DRAM technology, according to US prosecutors. Bo Gu and Masood Farivar also contributed to this report.</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/beijing-s-latest-strike-in-us-china-chip-war-may-hurt-china-experts-say/7105005.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/beijing-s-latest-strike-in-us-china-chip-war-may-hurt-china-experts-say/7105005.html</guid><pubDate> Tue, 23 May 2023 02:23:59 -0400</pubDate><category> China News</category><author> webdesk@voanews.com (Joyce Huang) </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/09680000-0a00-0242-3fe4-08da6dc255a8_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> China&#39;s Pioneering Gay Rights Group Halts Operations Under &#39;Force Majeure&#39;</title><description> The 15-year-old Beijing LGBT Center, one of the pioneers of the &quot;different sexual orientation movement&quot; in China, announced this week that it had terminated its operations without explanation. Analysts said the closure of the well-known rights center was seen as inevitable and a reflection of the increasingly repressive political environment in China under Xi Jinping. The LGBT Center released a statement on its social media accounts Monday evening, announcing that the center would cease operations &quot;due to force majeure.&quot; That legal phrase typically refers to events outside a party&#39;s control, although the message did not elaborate on the reasons. VOA Mandarin left a message on the center&#39;s account but has not received a response. As part of its public mission, the LGBT Center was committed to improving the environment for sexual minorities in China. Its main business included providing psychological counseling, rapid HIV screening and &quot;gender-friendly workplace training&quot; to promote gender diversity and prevent discrimination. The center has also sued organizations that administer electroshock therapy to homosexuals. Jennifer Lu, Asia program director of Outright International, a group focused on improving rights for sexual minorities around the world, has long been concerned with the situation in China. In an interview with VOA Mandarin, she said the sudden closure of the center was a shame, but that she wasn&#39;t surprised by it. She said many sexual minority activists have told her that they are unable to organize events in China and that there are fewer and fewer outlets to speak out. &quot;There are quite a few Chinese LGBT groups,&quot; Lu said, &quot;who may be warned by the public security officers or friends before they hold an event that &#39;this event has to be canceled.&#39; The worrying thing is that the people who try to talk them out of the events don&#39;t necessarily use a strong tone, but often hint, &#39;I know what you&#39;re doing.&#39; &quot;Or, the person who delivers the message would say, &#39;I know you&#39;ve had these conversations.&#39; These &#39;conversations&#39; are usually private or internal discussions. You then realize that some of the discussions or events that you prepare for are not secure. They are being monitored at all times.&quot; Homosexuality was decriminalized in China in 1997, but in recent years Beijing has officially restricted some kinds of LGBT content on television and social media. In 2017, the country&#39;s broadcasting authority banned the depiction of homosexuality, including it in the category of &quot;abnormal sexual behavior&quot; similar to incest. But a proposal in 2018 to ban all gay content from Weibo, the country&#39;s popular social media service, was reversed after public outcry. All LGBT groups at risk? In 2020, the Shanghai Pride Festival, China&#39;s largest multigender event, was discontinued, presumably because of pressure from Chinese authorities on the organizers. In 2021, social media accounts of sexual minority communities at several Chinese universities were shut down by WeChat, China&#39;s biggest social media platform. According to Lu, in the past few years, several Chinese sexual minority groups, including the Beijing LGBT Center, have faced various restrictions from the government and have planned to cease their operations, but some of them have been prevented from doing so by the authorities. Lu told VOA Mandarin: &quot;Some groups think, &#39;We might as well just shut down,&#39; since they can&#39;t hold events or do promotion or raise funds. But this is what the authorities want to avoid - to give the public an impression that civil society still exists. They don&#39;t want to draw too much attention when they carry out their so-called stability policy; they don&#39;t want controversy.&quot; The Beijing LGBT Center was a place for people &quot;to go to when they are under pressure in society or in their families, or to seek help when they are in trouble,&quot; Lu said. &quot;This is a very important and basic service in the LGBT movement. That&#39;s why people were so shocked by the sudden closure of the center.&quot; Taiwan amends gay marriage rules In 2019, Taiwan&#39;s Legislative Yuan passed the Special Act on Same-Sex Marriage, becoming the first country in Asia to allow same-sex marriage, but the regulations stipulated that married same-sex couples could adopt only children biologically related to one of the partners. The law was amended Tuesday when Taiwan&#39;s Legislative Yuan passed an amendment to officially open all adoptions to same-sex couples. In January, Taiwan expanded the reach of same-sex marriage. Taiwanese citizens can register for marriage in Taiwan regardless of whether the spouse&#39;s home country or region allows gay marriage, with one exception — China. Qi Jiawei, a veteran gay rights activist in Taiwan, told VOA Mandarin that Taiwan is now leading Asia in same-sex marriage legislation. &quot;Taiwan opened transnational [gay marriage] in the Lunar New Year of 2023. Homosexual people from any country in the world can get married in Taiwan, except those from mainland China,&quot; Qi said. &quot;The adoption from gay couples was not open at first, so Taiwan fixed this problem by making an amendment. So the last issue is solved now.&quot; Bo Gu contributed to this report.</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/china-s-pioneering-gay-rights-group-halts-operations-under-force-majeure-/7101614.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/china-s-pioneering-gay-rights-group-halts-operations-under-force-majeure-/7101614.html</guid><pubDate> Mon, 22 May 2023 21:16:07 -0400</pubDate><category> China News</category><author> webdesk@voanews.com (Victor Chin) </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/01000000-0aff-0242-9a61-08db58d884f1_cx0_cy8_cw0_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Florida Sued Over Law Blocking Chinese Citizens, Other Foreigners From Buying Property</title><description> A group of Chinese citizens living and working in the southern US state of Florida sued the state Monday over a new law that bans Chinese nationals from purchasing property in large swaths of the state. The law applies to properties within 16 kilometers of military installations and other “critical infrastructure” and also affects citizens of Cuba, Venezuela, Syria, Iran, Russia, and North Korea. But Chinese citizens and those selling property to them face the harshest penalties. The prohibition also applies to agricultural land. The American Civil Liberties Union says the law will have a substantial chilling effect on sales to Chinese and Asian people who can legally buy property. The suit says the law unfairly equates Chinese people with the actions of their government and says there is no evidence of national security risks from Chinese citizens buying Florida property. The law “will codify and expand housing discrimination against people of Asian descent in violation of the Constitution and the Fair Housing Act,” the ACLU said in a news release announcing the suit. “It will also cast an undue burden of suspicion on anyone seeking to buy property whose name sounds remotely Asian, Russian, Iranian, Cuban, Venezuelan, or Syrian.” US-China ties are strained amid growing tensions over security and trade. In nearly a dozen statehouses and Congress, a decades-old worry about foreign land ownership has spiked since a Chinese spy balloon traversed the skies from Alaska to South Carolina last month. Florida&#39;s Republican Governor Ron DeSantis, who is expected to launch a presidential campaign this week, signed the bill May 8. His office didn&#39;t immediately respond to an email seeking comment. The law is set to take affect July 1. Under the new regulation, it will be a felony for Chinese people to buy property in restricted areas or for any person or real estate company to knowingly sell to restricted people. For the other targeted nationals, the penalty is a misdemeanor for buyers and sellers. It applies to land near military instillations as well as land near infrastructure like airports and seaports, water and wastewater treatment plants, natural gas and oil processing facilities, power plants, spaceports, and telecommunications central switching offices. The ACLU says the law “will have the net effect of creating &#39;Chinese exclusion zones&#39; that will cover immense portions of Florida, including many of the state&#39;s most densely populated and developed areas.” “This impact is exactly what laws like the Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882 and the California Alien Land Law of 1913 did more than a hundred years ago,” the lawsuit says. Those on the restricted list that already own property near critical infrastructure must register with the state or face fines of up to $1,000 a day. They&#39;re also prohibited from acquiring additional property. The law has provisions to allow the state to seize property from violators. The number of states restricting foreign ownership of agricultural land has risen by 50% this year. Heading into 2023, 14 states had laws restricting foreign ownership or investments in private agricultural land. So far this year, restrictive laws also have been enacted in Arkansas, Idaho, Montana, Tennessee, Utah and Virginia. Foreign land ownership has become “a political flashpoint,” said Micah Brown, a staff attorney for the National Agricultural Law Center at the University of Arkansas. Brown said the recent surge in state laws targeting land ownership by foreign entities stems from some highly publicized cases of Chinese-connected companies purchasing land near military bases. Earlier this year, the US Air Force said that the Fufeng Group&#39;s planned $700 million wet corn milling plant near a base in Grand Forks, North Dakota, poses a “significant threat to national security.” After a Chinese army veteran and real estate tycoon bought a wind farm near an Air Force base in Texas, that state responded in 2021 by banning infrastructure deals with individuals tied to hostile governments, including China.</description><link/> https://www.voanews.com/a/florida-sued-over-law-blocking-chinese-citizens-other-foreigners-from-buying-property/7104519.html<guid> https://www.voanews.com/a/florida-sued-over-law-blocking-chinese-citizens-other-foreigners-from-buying-property/7104519.html</guid><pubDate> Mon, 22 May 2023 19:04:14 -0400</pubDate><category>美国</category><category>China News</category><author> webdesk@voanews.com (Associated Press) </author><enclosure length="0" type="image/jpeg" url="https://gdb.voanews.com/01000000-0aff-0242-85c7-08db5b160f9e_w800_h450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>